José Luis Gutiérrez Mendoza

Data Engineer

(+57) 300 5568793 <u>ing.joseluisgutierrez@gmail.com</u> <u>https://www.linkedin.com/in/ilgutierrezm/</u>

Data Engineer with more than 6 years of experience working on data exploitation projects in financial services, technology, government, logistics and transportation companies. Use of programming languages like **Python, SQL** and cloud platforms like **Azure**. I consider myself a self-taught person, who is always acquiring new knowledge especially in books.

EXPERIENCE

VISA, Colombia — Urban Mobility Specialist (July, 2021 -Present)

• During this time, I have contributed to the increased penetration of contactless cards in the country, which went from 50% to 53% and 31.1K of new transactions that to date have been carried out in the MIO-Cali transportation system. Thanks to the implementation of marketing strategies that are products of insights obtained from Dashboards.

Tech-Stack: Excel, Tableau, PowerBi and Power Point.

Agencia Nacional Digital, Colombia — Business Intelligence Expert (June, 2021 - November, 2021)

• Developed the Business Intelligence module of the country's Occupational Risk management software. Software that seeks to reduce by 30% the management times of processes related to occupational risks of Colombians.

Tech-Stack: Kimball, Python, SQLServer, SSIS, SSRS, GIT, Azure and Power Bl.

Ministerio de Justicia y el Derecho, Colombia — Analytics Leader — Colombia (October, 2019 - March, 2021)

- Implemented data components required for the data platform of the Colombian Drug Observatory. Components such
 as Pipelines, ETL's, SP's, Reports, Dashboards and statistical algorithms. Achieving get 100% control of the information
 related to topics such as the consumption, spraying, eradication, seizure and appearance of illicit drugs.
- Designed and implemented a systematized data exchange scheme between different entities of the justice sector, this allowed reducing the time of receipt of relevant information from 30 days to 1 day after the end of each month.

Tech-Stack: Kimball, Python, Tableau, SQL Server, SSIS, SSRS, GIT, Azure, and Power Bl.

Transportes Sanchez Polo, Colombia — Chief Technology Officer (February, 2011 - September, 2019)

- Implemented the Oracle Business Intelligence platform. This project made it possible to unify the information of the 3
 companies of the business group and consult it in Dashboards and Reports. Achieved a 17% reduction in operating
 costs and a 19% increase in the productivity of the automotive fleet.
- Designed and implemented a systematized data exchange scheme between different GPS system providers. With this
 tool, the company obtained improvements in the planning, operation, customer service and security processes by
 integrating 80% of the associated vehicles to the vehicle fleet.

Tech-Stack: Python, Java, Oracle, Oracle Cloud, PostgreSQL and PHP.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python (5+ YOE). SQL (8+ YOE)

Cloud Computing: Azure.

Frameworks and Tools: Pandas, Numpy, ScikitLearn, Spacy. OpenCV.

Database: SQL: MySQL, PostgreSQL,Oracle. NOSQL: MongoD **Languages:** Spanish, Native; English, Fluent; French, Intermediate;

EDUCATION

Master in Big Data and Business Analytics, Universidad de Nebrija - (In Progress)

Exam DP-201 Designing an Azure Data Solution, Microsoft - Mar 2021

Certification in Azure Data Scientist, Microsoft - Feb 2021

Exam 778: Analyzing and Visualizing Data with Power BI, Microsoft - Jan 2021 **Specialization in Big Data, University of California San Diego** - Sep 2020

Machine Learning, Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Aug 2019

Specialization in Software Engineering, Universidad del Norte - Nov 2011

Degree in Information Technology, Universidad Autonoma del Caribe - Jul 2011